In the next two videos, we're going to be looking at code generation for a language
在接下来的两个视频中，我们将了解一种语言的代码生成
that's higher level than a simple stack machine language we've been talking about
这比我们一直在讨论的简单堆栈机器语言级别更高
so far. So here's a language with integers and integer operation and this was the
到目前为止。这是一种带有整数和整数运算的语言，这是
grammar. So a program consists of a list of declarations, and what's a declaration?
语法。那么，一个程序由一系列声明组成，什么是声明呢？
A declaration is a function definition so it has a function name, the function takes
声明是一个函数定义，因此它有一个函数名，该函数采用
a list of arguments which are just identifiers, and the function has an
参数列表，这些参数只是标识符，并且该函数有一个
expression, which is the body of the function And what in function bodies look
表达式，它是函数体以及函数体中的外观
like, well they expressions can be integers identifiers if then else, and the
例如，如果Then Else，则它们的表达式可以是整数标识符，并且
only predicate that we're going to allow is an equality test between integers and
我们将允许的唯一谓词是整数和
then sums of expressions, differences of expressions, and function calls. Now we'll
然后是表达式的和、表达式的差异和函数调用。现在我们要
just say that the first function definition in the list is the entry point.
就说列表中的第一个函数定义是入口点。
This will be the main routine, or the function that gets run when the program
这将是主例程，或者是在程序运行时运行的函数
starts And this language is expressive enough to write a Fibonacci function And
开始，并且此语言具有足够的表现力，可以编写斐波那契函数和
here it is And this is just a standard definition, if X is one then the result is
这就是，这只是一个标准定义，如果X是1，那么结果是
zero. If X is two, the result is one. Otherwise it's the sum of fib of X minus
零。如果X是二，则结果是一。否则就是X的fib减去
one and fib of X minus two. Now, it's a two code generation for this language. We
一和X减去二的纤维。现在，这是这种语言的两个代码生成。我们
need to generate code for each expression E; we need to produce MIPS code for each
需要为每个表达式E生成代码；我们需要为每个表达式生成MIPS代码
expression E that accomplishes two things. First of all, that code is going to
表达式E完成两件事。首先，该代码将
compute the value of E, and leave it in the accumulator A zero. Right? So when the
计算E的值，并将其留在累加器A中为零。对吗？所以当
code for E is done, the value of E will be stored in the accumulator And furthermore,
E的代码完成后，E的值将存储在累加器中，而且，
E is going to, the code for E, excuse me, the generated code for E is going to
要，E的代码，打扰一下，E的生成代码要
preserve the stack pointer and the contents of the stack. That means whatever
保留堆栈指针和堆栈内容。那意味着什么都行
the stack is when we started executing E, or the code for E, the stack will be
堆栈是当我们开始执行E时，或者E的代码，堆栈将是
exactly the same after we're done, executing the code for E And we're going
在我们完成之后完全一样，执行E的代码，然后我们将
to write a code generation function C-gen of E that produces code. Okay? So C-gen
编写生成代码的E的代码生成函数C-gen。好吧?所以C世代
would be something that produces a program. It produces code that will
应该是制作程序的东西。它生成的代码将
accomplish these two things. Now our co-generation function is just going to
完成这两件事。现在我们的热电联产函数
work by cases And to begin with let's focus on the expressions, and we're just
按案例工作，首先让我们集中在表达式上，我们只是
going to have, different kind of code or a certain kind of code that's generated for
将有不同类型的代码或特定类型的代码为其生成
each kind of expression in the language. So to evaluate an expression, which is a
语言中的每一种表达方式。因此，要计算一个表达式，该表达式是
just an integral constant, all we have to do is load that constant into the
这只是一个整数常数，我们所要做的就是将该常数加载到
accumulator. So, the code generation for ‘I', for the constant, ‘I', is the
累加器。因此，常量“i”的“i”的代码生成是
instruction, load immediate into the accumulator the value of ‘I' And it's
指令中，将立即值“i”加载到累加器中，则它将
easy to see that this preserves the stack as required, so this doesn't modify the
很容易看出，这会根据需要保留堆栈，因此不会修改
stack pointer or the contents of the stack at all, so the stack is exactly the same
堆栈指针或堆栈的内容，所以堆栈是完全相同的
before and after the execution of this instruction. >> And another thing I want
在执行此指令之前和之后。>>还有一件事我想要
to point out or I want to emphasize here, is I'm going to be following a convention
我要指出或者我想在这里强调的是，我将遵循一个惯例
that things that are in red, are things that are done at compile time And things
红色的东西，是在编译时做的东西
that are in blue are things that are going to be done in run time. So in this case,
蓝色的是要在运行时完成的事情。所以在这种情况下，
at compile time we execute the function C gen of I And that produces code. Here that
在编译时，我们执行i的函数Cgen，生成代码。在这里，那个
will run at run time, okay. So, C gen of I, something that would execute a compile
将在运行时运行，好的。所以，第i代的C语言可以执行编译
time, and it produces a program that will be executed at run time And this is to
时间，它会生成一个将在运行时执行的程序，这是为了
help you separate in your mind, and, and to develop a very, firm grip on the idea
帮助你在脑海中分离，并发展出对这个想法非常，坚定的把握
that we have a real division of time in these programs, There's stuff that happens
我们在这些节目中有一个真正的时间划分，有一些事情会发生
inside the compiler, and then there's computation that's deferred until the
在编译器内部，然后有计算被推迟到
program that we are producing, actually executes. All right, now let's look at
我们正在制作的程序，实际上正在执行。好的，现在我们来看一下
another example. Let's, let's take on the addition of two expressions and think
再举一个例子。让我们来看看这两个表达式的加法，然后想一想
about the code that gets generated for that. So, what are we going to do? Well
关于为此生成的代码。那么，我们要做什么呢？井
the first thing that happens when we execute E1+E2 is that we have to compute
当我们执行E1+E2时发生的第一件事是，我们必须计算
the values of the sum expressions, we have to know what integers we're going to add.
求和表达式的值，我们必须知道要加的整数是什么。
So we better generate code for E1. And that's going to happen at com pile time.
所以我们最好为E1生成代码。这将在COM编译时间发生。
We're definitely going to generate that code at compile time. And then, once we've
我们肯定会在编译时生成该代码。然后，一旦我们
got the value of E1, well, remember we only have one, register stack machine, so
得到e1的值，好的，记住我们只有一个，寄存器堆栈机器，所以
we're going to have to save that value somewhere until we also know the value of
我们将不得不将该值保存在某个地方，直到我们也知道
E2 and where we're going to put it. We'll do what we always do; we'll put it on a
E2和我们要把它放在哪里。我们会像往常一样做；我们会把它放在
stack. So, E1 The, the, the code for E1 is guaranteed to leave the value of E1 and
堆栈。所以E1的这个，这个，E1的代码保证离开E1的值，
the accumulator. So what we're going to store the value of E1 onto the stack. And
累加器。所以我们要把E1的值存储到堆栈上。和
we know how to do that. We store A0 onto the stack, and then we have to bump the
我们知道怎么做。我们将A0存储到堆栈中，然后我们必须将
stack pointer. >> And then we can generate code for E2. Okay and again, this stuff in
堆栈指针。>>然后我们就可以为E2生成代码了。好的，再说一遍，这些东西在
blue is a part of the program that will be executed at, at run time. These are calls
蓝色是程序的一部分，将在运行时执行。这些都是电话
to the co-generator that are happening at compile time. And so we generate the code
传递给编译时正在发生的联合生成器。因此我们生成代码
for E2, and then that goes here after this code for pushing the value of E1 on the
对于E2，则在此代码之后将E1的值推送到
stack And once we have the value for E2, now we can perform the add, So how do we
堆栈，一旦我们有了E2的值，现在我们就可以执行加法了，那么我们该如何
do that? Well, first we retrieve the value of E1. So we load the value of E1 Which is
这样做吗？那么，首先我们检索e1的值。所以我们加载e1的值，它是
on the stack. And notice that. This works because E2 is guaranteed the code for E2
在堆栈上。注意这一点。这是可行的，因为向E2保证了E2的代码
is guaranteed to preserve the stack. You know this code for E2 here, and let me
保证保留堆栈。你知道E2的这个密码吗，让我
digress for a moment; this code for E2 can be arbitrarily complicated. This could be
暂时跑题；E2的这段代码可以任意复杂。这可能是
a whole program. It could go call functions. It could allocate data
一个完整的计划。它可以调用函数。它可以分配数据
structures. It could print things out. It could do all kinds of complicated things
结构。它可以把东西打印出来。它可以做各种复杂的事情
But because we have this invariant that all code generation for all expressions
但是因为我们有这个不变量，所有表达式的所有代码生成
will preserve the stack, we know that no matter how complicated this is and how
将保留堆栈，我们知道无论这有多复杂，有多复杂
long it takes. When it's done executing, the stack will be in the same state. And
这需要很长时间。当它完成执行时，堆栈将处于相同的状态。和
that's what allows us to know. Where to find the value of E1 that we stored away
这就是我们能知道的。在哪里可以找到我们存储的e1的值
It's going to be at the top of the stack, Okay, so we load the value B one back into
它将位于堆栈的顶部，好的，所以我们将值B加回到
a temporary register, now we can do the add Okay, so we add T1 and A0 together,
一个临时寄存器，现在我们可以做加法了好的，所以我们把T1和A0加在一起，
and store that back in the accumulator And now we have to pop the stack And now
并将其存储回累加器，现在我们必须弹出堆栈
notice that this is all the code, here, for E1+E2, and when we're done, we've,
注意，这里是E1+E2的所有代码，当我们完成后，我们已经，
established our the value of E1+E2 is in the accumulator. That was established by
建立了我们的E1+E2的值在累加器中。它是由
this instruction. And this pop here restores the state of the stacks. Now, the
这份指示。这里的弹出窗口恢复了堆栈的状态。现在，
state of the stacks here is exactly what it was when we entered this block of code
这里的堆栈状态与我们输入这段挡路代码时的情况一模一样
up here. Now to be completely precise I really should write this code generation
在这上面。现在，完全准确地说，我真的应该编写这个代码生成
function out a slightly different way And that would be like this. So what we're
以一种稍有不同的方式来实现，就像这样。所以我们要做的是
really doing here is we are generating code for E1 and then we're printing out
我们在这里真正做的是为E1生成代码，然后打印输出
into a file or something like that the code to do the push. Okay, and then we
放入文件或类似的文件中，即执行推送的代码。好的，然后我们
generate the code for U2 And now, these calls, the code generation, are also
为U2生成代码，现在，这些调用，代码生成，也
printing in to the same file, okay. So, here, you know, they just printed out
打印到同一个文件，好的。所以，在这里，你知道，他们只是打印出来
the instructions, whatever the instructions are, like security one, this
指令，不管指令是什么，就像安全指令一样，这个
is printing out the code to execute, to do the push. You print out the code to do U2
打印出要执行的代码，进行推送。你打印出做U2的代码
And then, we print out the code to do the ad and the pop Fence. Yes, The add and the
然后，我们打印出做广告和流行围栏的代码。是的，加法和
pop. Okay, and this is just a, this is much more verbose over here, and so I'm
爸爸。好的，这只是一个，这里要冗长得多，所以我
trying to go in and leave out the prints and just indicate in blue the instructions
试着进去，去掉指纹，只用蓝色标明说明书
that are deferred, but I hope you understand what this means. Everything in
但我希望你能理解这意味着什么。里面的所有东西
red here, of course is being done in compile time so you know, we're calling
这里的红色当然是在编译时完成的，所以您知道，我们调用
these co-generation functions a compile time. The print statements are being
这些联合生成函数在编译时执行。打印语句正在
executed in compile time and then we're accumulating somewhere in some data
在编译时执行，然后我们在某些数据中积累
structure or in a file, all the instructions that will be executed at run
结构或文件中，将在运行时执行的所有指令
time. So let's think about a possible optimization to this code. Instead of
时间到了。因此，让我们考虑一下对此代码进行可能的优化。而不是
pushing the result of E1 on the stack, what if we stored the result of E1 in a
将E1的结果推送到堆栈上，如果我们将E1的结果存储在
temporary register T1. What would the code for that look like? >> Well in that world,
临时寄存器T1。它的代码会是什么样子？>>在那个世界里，
to generate code for E1 plus E2, what would we do? We'd generate code for E1 and
要为E1和E2生成代码，我们应该做什么？我们会为E1生成代码，然后
that would be followed now by instead of pushing the result on the stack, we would
现在，我们将不在堆栈上推送结果，而是
take the result of E1, which of course is in the accumul ator A0, we would store it
取E1的结果，它当然在累加器A0中，我们将存储它
in a temporary register And then we would generate code for E2. Alright, that we
在临时寄存器中，然后我们将为E2生成代码。好的，那我们
followed by the code for E2, and then we could just do the add. We would, take the
然后是E2的代码，然后我们就可以做加法了。我们会，拿着
result of E2, which is in the accumulator A0, add it to the contents of T1, and
在累加器A0中的E2的结果，将其与T1的内容相加，并且
store that into the accumulator A0, and of course there's no pushing and popping from
将其存储到累加器A0中，当然不会从
the stack here, so this code preserves the stack, and it looks like, anyway, that it
这里的堆栈，所以这段代码保留了堆栈，不管怎么说，看起来它
actually puts the value of E1 plus E2, into, the accumulator. Unfortunately, this
实际上把E1加E2的值放入累加器。不幸的是，这
code is incorrect, so this is actually wrong, and you don't want to do this And
代码不正确，因此这实际上是错误的，您不希望这样做，并且
to see why, let's consider what would happen. If, E2 Was itself the actually,
要了解原因，让我们来考虑一下会发生什么。如果E2本身就是真正的
let's do it for a concrete example. Let's do the example one plus two Plus three
让我们来做一个具体的例子。让我们来做这个一加二加三的例子
Parenthesize like that, okay. So what's going to happen, so E1 here, so we're
像这样插入，好的。接下来会发生什么，所以E1在这里，所以我们
doing one plus two plus three. So this will be a load immediate, the first, the
做一加二加三。所以这将是一个立即的负载，第一个，
code for E1 will be a load immediate into A0 of the number one. Okay, and then we'll
E1的代码将直接加载到数字1的A0中。好的，然后我们
have the move. We'll try to save that value I, in, temporary register T1. And
开始行动吧。我们将尝试将该值i1保存在临时寄存器t1中。和
now we're going to generate code for E2. And what's E2? Well, E2 is itself, a plus
现在我们将为E2生成代码。那么E2是什么呢？嗯，E2本身就是一个加号
expression. So we're going to recursively call the code generator to generate code
表达式。所以我们将递归调用代码生成器来生成代码
for two+3. So we generate code for the new first, expression. So that will be a
2+3。所以我们为新的第一个表达式生成代码。所以这将是一个
load immediate, into A0 of the value two And now you should be able to
将IMMEDIATE加载到值2的A0中，现在您应该能够
see what's going to go wrong, because. Since this uses the same co-generation
看看会出什么问题，因为。因为这使用相同的热电联产
strategy, it's also going to try to use T-1 to hold the temporary value. So it's
战略，它还将尝试使用T-1来保持临时价值。所以这就是
going to move the accumulator into T-1, thereby clobbering the value of the
将累加器移到T-1，从而重写
previous self expression that we had evaluated, the number one. Okay, so that
我们之前评估过的自我表达，排名第一。好的，那就是说
value's going to be overwritten and then we're going to do and add  And oops I may
值将被覆盖，然后我们将进行加法运算，哦，我可能会
have made a mistake, we're not going to do an ad, let me erase that Forgot to
犯了个错误，我们不做广告了，让我把忘了的抹去吧
generate the code for the three, so now we load the value of three. I, in to the
生成这三个参数的代码，所以现在我们加载值为3。我，在到了
accumulator And now we can do the add, now comes the add And so we do A0 T1 A0 and
累加器，现在我们可以做加法了，现在加法来了，所以我们做A0，T1，A0和
when you execute this what do you get. You get two + three which is five and that's
当你执行这个的时候，你会得到什么。你得到2+3等于5，那就是
fine but now, Now we have the value of this sub expression. In the accumulator
好的，但是现在，我们有了这个子表达式的值。在累加器中
and now ready to do the outer add. So that generates another add instruction. Which
现在可以进行外部加法了。所以这会生成另一条加法指令。哪一个
is exactly the same But unfortunately, the first value of T1, the first temporary we
是完全相同的，但不幸的是，t1的第一个值，第一个临时的
tried to restore has been overwritten And so what's in that, what's in T1 at this
尝试恢复的内容已被覆盖，因此，T1中的内容如下所示
point is the value two, instead of the value one, and we get that one+2+3=7.
point是值2，而不是值1，我们得到1+2+3=7。
Which is not what we wanted And so the problem here of course is that in the
这不是我们想要的，所以这里的问题当然是在
presence of nested expressions, and particularly nested expressions of the
嵌套表达式的存在，特别是
same kind, if the expressions try to use a fixed register for their temporary
如果表达式尝试将固定寄存器用于其临时寄存器，则返回相同类型的
values, then if you try to generate a code for two different expressions that are
值，则如果您尝试为两个不同的表达式生成代码，这两个表达式分别是
nested - sorry two expressions of the same kind that are nested beside each
嵌套-抱歉，每个表达式旁边嵌套了两个相同类型的表达式
other, they will step on each other's temporary intermediate results And so
其他的，他们会踩到对方的临时中间结果，所以
that's why we have to use a stack to store intermediate values. So this example
这就是为什么我们必须使用堆栈来存储中间值。所以这个例子
illustrates a couple of features of code generation that I just want to emphasize.
说明了我只想强调的几个代码生成功能。
First of all, notice that the code for plus is really a template that has holes
首先，注意加号的代码实际上是一个有漏洞的模板
in it for the code, for evaluating E1, E2, that is there are some fixed instructions,
它里面对代码，对E1，E2求值，就是有一些固定的指令，
that we admit And then there are places where we plug in the code for E one and
我们承认，然后在某些地方，我们插入E One的代码，
the code for E two, okay, so that's what I mean by a template, so there's some fixed
E2的代码，好的，这就是我所说的模板，所以有一些固定的
stuff which are the instructions that actually do the ad, and then there's a
这些东西是实际做广告的指令，然后有一个
place where we can just plug directly in, arbitrary code, whatever it is for
我们可以直接插入任意代码的地方，不管它是用来做什么的
implementing E one and E two, and we'll see the same pattern with all the other
实现E1和E2，我们将看到与所有其他的模式相同的模式
kinds of expressions. The other important point is that stack machine code,
各种各样的表情。另一个要点是堆栈机器代码，
generation is recursive. That is you know the code for E1 plus E2 is code for E1 and
生成是递归的。也就是说，E1加E2的代码是E1的代码，
E2 glued together and recursively regenerate code E1 and E2 which will have
E2粘合在一起并递归地重新生成代码E1和E2
their own templates and may even be other expressions of the same kind as we just
它们自己的模板，甚至可能是与我们刚才所说的相同类型的其他表达式
saw And what this means is that code generation can be written as a recursive
这意味着可以将代码生成编写为递归
descent of the abstract syntax tree, at least for the expressions. Alright so
抽象语法树的下降，至少对于表达式是这样。好的，那么
let's consider another new instruction. Let's add the subtraction instruction And
让我们考虑另一条新指令。让我们添加减法指令并
this is just like addition instruction so sub just subtraction to register instead
这就像加法指令一样，所以SUB只需减去寄存器即可
of adding them. And code generation then for subtraction expression as you might
把它们加进去。然后为减法表达式生成代码，就像您可能做的那样
imagine look and awful like code generation for a plus expression. So what
想象一下，加号表达式的代码生成看起来很可怕。那又怎样
do we have first we have a place where we plug in the code for E1. >> Then we have
我们有没有，首先，我们有一个地方，我们把E1的代码插进去。>>那么我们就有
to store the value of E1 on the stack. We have to remember that intermediate result
将E1的值存储在堆栈上。我们必须记住中间结果
And then we can go off and compute the value of E2. So this is where the code for
然后我们就可以开始计算E2的值了。这就是代码的位置
E2 gets plugged in And then at the end, we load the value of E1 back into a temporary
E2接通电源，然后在最后，我们将E1的值加载回临时
register. I actually do the operation, the subtraction, and then pop the stack And
注册。我实际上做了运算，减法，然后弹出堆栈
the thing to do note about this code is that it's exactly the same as the code for
关于此代码需要注意的是，它与
addition except for this instruction right here where we do a subtraction instead of
加法，除了这里的这条指令，我们在这里做减法，而不是
an add.
一个Add。